Benjamin Luft collection of 9-11 first responders' oral histories
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Oral History Interviews, April 9, 2010 through November 4, 2016
  - Edward Wurglics oral history interview conducted by Melodie Guerrera, November 16, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 071
    Edward is a NYC Department of Transportation worker with 26 years of service. On 9/11, he was working in his present job and had taken an annual day off from work to go fishing on the Jersey Shore with his friend Tommy. They heard over 1010 Wins about a plane that hit the towers, and when they stopped to take out their binoculars, they saw the second plane hit the tower. Right away, he thought “We're under attack.” He rushed home via Ocean Parkway over the Robert Moses Bridge and went to work. He remembers there was mandatory overtime and everyone was on emergency standby. After his shift, he packed his gloves, vest, and helmet and proceeded to the site. He remembers, “I couldn’t breathe, my nose was clogged, my eyes were burning.” He got an id tag and walked four blocks to the site. He said, “Standing there, I thought I was on another planet.” He was ready to jump in and do anything and so went around asking cops, ironworkers and firemen what he could do. He was amazed at how people came together “naturally” and how people concentrated on what they did. He remembers, “It didn’t matter whether you had a uniform on…there was no rank,” and that it was different from standard New York attitudes. He worked on the bucket brigade as a volunteer, leaving his job at 5:30 PM and driving into the city to volunteer from 6:30 PM to 2 A.M. He recalls that “There was no night or day.” He got fatigued by working there. He gradually accepted that they wouldn’t find survivors and did not go into detail about work at the site. When he came home he couldn’t eat his supper, and couldn’t explain to his wife or kids what he heard or saw. He says however that he would do this experience again as “It was a good feeling knowing you’re trying to make a difference in this world.”
    - Moving Images
  - Anthony oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, November 29, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 072
    Anthony was a sergeant in the NYPD. He was at his Brooklyn precinct on 9-11-2001, and heard transmission over the radio about the towers being attacked. He actually saw the second plane hit the tower. He asked his superior at the precinct if he could take 10-15 officers to help out at the site, but he was required to secure the perimeter around his precinct first. He remembers that he wanted very much to be at the site rescuing people, and states, “We were (all) there for that…we had an army.” Anthony went to Ground Zero the next day. All parkways were closed on 9-12-2001 and travel to his precinct was quick. He proceeded to start working twelve hour shifts, from 6 a.m. to 6p.m. He remembers that all roadways south of Canal Street were closed to traffic, and that there were dust plumes in the air and people’s faces were pasted with soot and dust. He said the main danger for responders at the time was loose debris, and not toxins. Anthony was also in law school at this time, and mentions how he had to juggle his work as a sergeant, his family commitments, and school. He attended about 10-15 funerals. Two of his close buddies in the Emergency Services Unit passed away. Anthony describes the police officer funerals in detail, and said afterwards that the experience was both desensitizing and patriotic. Anthony states for the most part he does not feel he did anything heroic at the site, but “Those people who went above and beyond the call of duty deserve to be called heroes.”
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - John James McHale oral history interview conducted by Dr. Benjamin Luft, November 30, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 073
    John was a police officer in Rochester, New York on 9-11-2001. He was driving alone in his patrol car, when he heard on the radio that the World Trade Center Tower was hit by a plane. He went to his headquarters and asked to sign up on a waitlist to see if they needed responders at the site. He had also previously worked in the NYPD for 6 years, and called up his former partner, John, in Brooklyn to see if they needed help. He took vacation time and traveled 5 ½ hours down to Manhattan to see if he could help. As he approached the Westside Highway, he recalled smelling burning flesh. John went to the Javits Center and was bussed to the site with a group of NYPD officers from the Manhattan area. He says he was the odd in his Rochester Police uniform. He came into the site through Vesey Street and recalled seeing just rubble, smoke, and dust—and had only a painter’s mask on. He felt it was unorganized that first day, and relied mostly on Lieutenant Ortiz, who took roll call and delegated tasks to other responders. John worked on the bucket brigade and was told to tag body parts or “anything of substantial value”. He had never done anything like that before, but still felt it was part of his job. He stayed at the site for 15-16 hours, and by the end of the day drove back to Long Island with his former NYPD partner to get some rest. He slept for 3-4 hours and drove back to the Brooklyn precinct and was taken again to the Vesey Street area. He recalls how female officers were more expressive with their emotions than male officers, but how everyone comforted each other when needed. He felt the second day was more organized than the first and by the third day they had organized trucks bringing in blue jeans and Timberland boots that responders could use and dispose of. He recalls that he never ate so many granola bars in his life. For bathrooms they had port-a-potties and resources got better as time went on. His friend Paul from upstate New York also managed to arrange rooms at upscale New York hotels after working at the site. John recalls that this experience was tough on his family and his wife would ask him why he volunteered. He remembers that around two months after this experience he received a magazine in the mail that had pictures of responders who died on 9-11, and this made him breakdown a little bit. His wife was there to comfort him, and sometimes his kids still ask questions. He also mentioned that he had brought a disposable camera with him to take some pictures of the site, and has some pictures mounted on his wall at home. He feels the positives to come out of this tragedy was that people learned to work together in times of crisis.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Greta Helmke oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, December 1, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 074
    Greta is the widow of Robert (Rob) who was a police officer. They were married in 1998 and had 2 children. Greta stated that her husband loved his job and followed in his father’s footsteps. They both grew up in Merrick, Long Island and met in their late 20s. Robert graduated from the police academy in 1995 and was assigned to the medical division in Queens. Greta was a buyer for Fortunoff's (she has worked as a buyer for 20 years and has travelled to many places around the world). At the time of 9/11, they were young and just starting their lives and planning for the future. That morning, they were on vacation in Canada and Greta was pregnant with their first child. When they heard the news, Rob immediately said, “We have to go back”. There was no convincing him to remain on vacation. They drove all night, approximately 10 hours to get home. Greta stated that even in Canada things were shut down because no one exactly knew what had happened. They drove in silent shock pretty much the entire ride home. Rob left for work as soon as they got back home and he was assigned to the security perimeter at the WTC. The next few months were a blur; at times Rob slept at work, and when home, he didn’t talk much about what was happening. Their first child, a son, was born in March, just a few months after 9/11. Greta states that Rob had changed. He began to lose weight, slept a lot, and was just “never quite right”. He always had dark circles under his eyes and despite several doctor visits and tests, nothing was diagnosed except anemia. By the time they finally discovered that he had a rare form of intestinal cancer, it was stage 4 and incurable. He had a series of operations and lengthy hospital stays trying to prolong his life but nothing worked. She watched her husband wither from 180 pounds to under 100 before he passed away. Her daughter, their 2nd child, was only 3 when Rob passed away. Greta states that it was difficult having 2 children but she had support from friends and neighbors. Her father had been a deacon and they had a lot of people from the church that were available to help as well. Greta states that her husband was proud of what he did and his contribution to 9/11. She uses the word "hero" only when speaking to her children about her their father, otherwise, she said that Rob, like many others, was just doing his job didn't consider himself to be a hero. They had no regrets but did ask why. They were young, newly married and just starting out in life. They had so little time together. Greta is sometimes angry but mostly accepting, doing what she needs to do to keep her family together. Greta says that life can be very lonely, but she has bonded with others in similar situations and has recently joined John Feal in creating a project for 9/11 responders and their families. She has also been to Washington to speak on the healthcare bill and to help keep the memories alive. She is and will always be proud of her husband and what he did and will kept telling her story. She will ‘never forget’ and she wants others to do the same.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - James Vaz oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, December 1, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 075
    Jim moved to Long Island in 1985 from the island of Jamaica. He became a volunteer firefighter because he wanted to serve his community, and later became an EMT as well. He is married and has 2 grown sons. At the time of 9/11, he was living in Bellport and said that there was a great ‘sense of community’ in the area. Jim managed the fire alarm systems at Brookhaven National Labs and also did fire rescue training at the fire academy. On 9/11, Jim was at work at Brookhaven Labs. He heard what happened on the news but wasn’t sure what had really happened until the 2nd plane hit. Then he knew it was an act of terrorism. He and his co-workers, other volunteer firefighters, wanted to go to the site immediately. Jim was the 2nd assistant chief at the time at the Brookhaven firehouse. He had to follow the rules and procedures and was told that he and his co-workers could not go, so he and 5 of his co-workers sat and waited. On 9/12, Jim and some of his co-workers realized that one of their team was missing. His name was Link and he was Jim’s best friend and like a brother. They called his home and were told by his wife that Link went to work. It only took a few minutes for them to realize that Link went on his own to the World Trade Center site. So at that moment, tired of waiting for orders, Jim and 4 others gathered some gear, piled into one car and headed into the city. They didn’t care what happened to them, they only knew they had to go and find their brother. Jim told his wife and sons that they were leaving, that they had to do what they had to do. Since they had identification as firefighters, they weren’t questioned on the way into the city. His co-worker, nicknamed Chicken Legs, drove the car on the expressway and they headed to Ladder 24 in midtown. They picked up more gear, drove as close as they could and then walked to the site. When they arrived at the site, Jim couldn’t believe the scene. He said he will never forget the vision of no color, only gray dust. Street signs couldn’t be read but because he knew the city, he guided the others in. As they approached the site it started raining. They saw lights and the skeleton of buildings. He said, “Wow, how could this happen? Why would anyone want to bring a giant to its knees?" This made him angry. They went to Engine 10 at the base of the WTC, where they were welcomed and sent to work on the pile. Once there, they tried to figure out where their friend might be. They said that Link would go to where the action was, probably at the top of the building. Since the building had collapsed, they started looking through the smoldering rubble at the base of one of the towers. They wedged in between and through any openings they could find. Jim said they were like gophers and moles just crawling and winding their way through any hole going further into the rubble trying to find Link. After many hours and finding nothing, they came out. They were wet, dirty, and tired but then found dry clothes and food. Jim and another co-worker nicknamed Maggot worked on the bucket brigade for a few days. He said it was organized chaos on the pile--manual labor searching for anything, sifting for life. After a week, Jim and his co-workers had to leave. Since they were technically never officially sent there to work, they were not getting paid from their regular jobs. He said it was heartbreaking to leave without having found his friend or anyone else. They headed home. Jim had helped Link get certified in scuba diving. Their plan was to eventually open a scuba/dive shop in the Cayman Islands when they retired. Link got his nickname because he always wore shorts no matter how cold out it was and he had skinny legs like links. A month after 9/11, another group of firefighters found Link. In memory of his fallen brother, Jim wears shorts to all events now and has a beer in honor of his friend. Jim said lessons learned are to be aware and cautious, that we are vulnerable. He also said that terrorists should know that we are one nation under God, we are a strong nation, we will prevail and we will fight for our freedom.
    - Moving Images
    - Graphic Materials
    - Manuscripts
  - Thomas oral history interview conducted by Michael Vetrano, December 2, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 076
    Thomas is a 37-year old disabled NYPD detective retired since March 2010 due to his 9/11 injuries. He worked at the 106th Precinct in Ozone Park, Queens, and also worked for the anti-crime unit investigating violent felonies, street crimes, and doing undercover work. He had worked the evening of 9/10 and was home on the morning of 9/11, when he received a phone call from his aunt asking him to try and locate his uncle, a senior vice president at Marsh and McLennan. Thomas felt unaffected emotionally and went into “fight or flight” mode, packed up some clothes and raced to his precinct in Queens. He said he could see the smoke from the Southern State Parkway as he was driving into the city and it was “eerily” quiet. When he arrived at the precinct it was “utter chaos.” Eventually groups were organized to go to Ground Zero. Later that day, he travelled on a city bus to the site and saw crowds walking out of Manhattan. He travelled with about 40 cops on the bus and said it was “dead quiet.” Thomas had previously witnessed gruesome sights, but nothing compared to this disaster: “No one could have been prepared for this.” He described the site when he first arrived as very disorganized with poor visibility, debris everywhere, and it was getting dark. Thomas went to Deutsche Bank where there was a temporary morgue and unzipped the body bags to try and locate his uncle. Outside of the morgue there was a big box of wallets with credit cards, etc. and pocketbooks. It was then that the gravity of the situation hit him. He was at Ground Zero for about 2-3 days straight and spent time on the bucket brigade. The smells were distinctive—flesh, human hair, and plastic. He called his aunt and told her what he knew. He hung a picture of his uncle in the hospital, even though he knew it was fruitless since his uncle was on one of the higher floors in the Trade Center. He witnessed fights between firemen and the NYPD and met with an officer he went to the academy with who was posted in front of four refrigerator trucks whose job it was to log in body parts. “We were all like zombies,” he said. His eyes, nose, and mouth were constantly filled with dust. He felt numb the whole time and was frustrated with the lack of urgency, but now understands why. He does not feel like a hero, he was just doing his job. After the event, Thomas was proud to be a NYC police officer. One month after 9/11 his family had a memorial for his uncle. A year later, two state troopers and a priest knocked on his aunt’s door with a one centimeter piece of bone. He described that as a setback for his aunt and his family since they were just beginning to recover from the passing of his uncle. Thomas knew two police officers and three firemen killed in the attacks. He tried to go to as many funerals as he could and tried not to become emotional. The whole event did not hit him until about five years after 9/11. He had delayed feelings and couldn’t talk about it for the first five years but now he finally can. He said media images trigger it and “it seems like everyone forgets.” Thomas thinks we have to look out and protect ourselves and be vigilant because they are “going to get us again.” He had no protection for the first three days at Ground Zero and received only a paper mask on the fourth day. A week later respirators were given to only lieutenants and higher ranking personnel. He did, however, mention at the end of his interview that he spent some time at the landfill where he was provided with a Tyvek suit and a respirator. He got the “9/11 cough" and now suffers from COPD, asthma, and rhinitis. He feels no one had the right protection and the event was very costly to him. He is disappointed that the event ruined his good career. He can no longer physically do his job and became out of breath just teaching his daughter how to ride a bike. Thomas originally wanted to be an architect but chose to be a police officer in order to help people. He loves to cook and is now pursuing a career as a chef.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Haydn Chacana oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, December 3, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 077
    On 9/11 Hadyn was a rookie for the NYPD at the 111th Precinct in Bayside, Queens. He had graduated from the Police Academy at age 25 in June of 2001. He was home on the morning of the attacks and saw the event unfold on TV. His initial reaction was shock. Hadyn was called to work on 9/11 and was assigned to an entrance ramp on the LIE to check IDs and make sure only authorized personnel were driving on the LIE. He was on the ramp alone from noon to about midnight until someone came and picked him up. He arrived at Ground Zero on 9/13/01 and didn’t know what to expect—he was scared. He travelled on an MTA bus and said it was quiet on the bus and he could see a “big cloud” over downtown. The bus took him near the Brooklyn Bridge which he described as a “ghost town, like something out of a movie.” He had a paper mask and he could only see a few feet in front of him. There were no civilians there, just policemen, FDNY, and the military. He did 12-hour shifts at the Federal Reserve Bank and for about 2-3 months he was assigned to perimeter security. Once he arrived at the site, his fear vanished. He saw the pile—a mound of metal stories high. It was like nothing he’d ever seen before. He worked for two weeks straight, getting only about four hours of sleep a night. He thought people were on edge. A childhood friend named Deborah was missing, and he later found out she had been killed in the attacks. He volunteered on the bucket brigade because he felt the need to help, but only did it twice. He did not see any body parts, but did see families sitting waiting for the recovery of a body. Haydn was angry about the attacks and had a hatred of the terrorists. He was frustrated that the terrorists had no rules, yet we did. As a rookie, he said the attacks had a “desensitizing” effect on him. He never felt like a hero, but the appreciation felt good. He would do it again and he was glad to see the “community unity” and how the event brought people together. He feels the feeling went away in a few months and “people had already forgotten.” He says he definitely appreciates things more, and said you “should take the opportunity when you have it-- it might not always be there.”
    - Moving Images
  - Danielle Bonge oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, December 3, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 078
    Danielle was a transformer mechanic for ConEd on 9/11. She was home that morning and watched the events unfold on TV. She felt a “pulling” to go to the site and drove there at 11PM that night. She did not know how to get there, but just followed the smoke and the burning smell. When she arrived at Ground Zero, she saw soot, smoke, and fires and said there were “papers flying everywhere.” In the chaos, she didn’t know what to do once she arrived. She left and returned with her video camera the next morning, feeling the need to document the site. She saw firemen sleeping in the street, and hoped to rescue someone. While on the bucket brigade, she found an intact teddy bear in mounds of soot with the inscription “Top of the World, World Trade Center, New York City.” She brought the teddy bear, still covered in dust, to this interview. Danielle says she was on a mission to help someone. She assisted some nurses she met at McDonalds, which was set up as NYPD headquarters, to set up supplies. The most difficult part for her is that after a few days she wasn’t allowed to help. She does not feel like a “hero,” but the event inspired her to join the volunteer fire department for five years. Recently, Danielle went to the site and said it was very emotional. “My life has been forever changed and the innocence is gone. You don’t feel safe anymore.” She is now very suspicious of people and finds it hard to trust others. She cherishes her family and doesn’t take things for granted, and believes so many more people have been affected by the attacks than just those who passed. She lives every day in their honor. Danielle is haunted by the event and hopes that we never forget all the lives that were affected. She believes we have to look at what happened so we can make it better, and is proud to be an American. Danielle stated she would do it again in a heartbeat, and that it was painful not to go to Katrina. She has a compulsion to go to disasters to help. As a result of the few days she spent at Ground Zero, she has nasal problems, sleep apnea, and GERD. She is glad she came to the WTC Program for help and feels she has been treated gently and with compassion.
    - Moving Images
    - Manuscripts
  - Ronald Nullet oral history interview conducted by Julie Broihier, December 6, 2010, AFC 2015/048: 079